<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<post>
  <title>A Day of DevOps, Release Management, Software Quality and Agile Project Requirements Management</title>
  <slug>a-day-of-devops-release-management-software-quality-and-agile-project-requirements-management</slug>
  <shortUrl>http://bit.ly/1qxVYfa</shortUrl>
  <author></author>
  <pubDate>2014-09-03 07:43:22</pubDate>
  <lastModified>2015-07-21 11:58:30</lastModified>
  <content>&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately there is no TechEd Africa this year – Microsoft have opted to go for smaller, more focused sessions in multiple cities (or at least that’s what I gather). I think it’s a shame, since the TechEd Africa event was always fantastic – and who doesn’t like getting out the office for a couple of days?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Anyway, the good news is that Microsoft are hosting “A Day of DevOps, Release Management, Software Quality and Agile Project Requirements Management” in Cape Town (Wed 10th at Crystal Towers Hotel) and in Johannesburg (on Mon 15th at the Microsoft offices on William Nicol). I’ll be presenting at both events, so make sure you get along.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The event has 2 themes – DevOps in the morning and Agile Project Management in the afternoon. You can attend one or the other or both events.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I’m particularly excited about the DevOps session – here’s some of the content that I’ll be covering:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;Release management and automation, release pipelines and approvals to accelerate deployment to operations, including using DSC, Chef and Puppet&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Treating Configuration as Code&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Application Insights&amp;nbsp; &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Cloud Based Load Testing&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Production Debugging and Monitoring&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Leveraging Azure for DevOps and Dev/Test Environments&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;System Centre and TFS Integration&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;For more details, go to the Microsoft SA Developer blog post &lt;a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/b/southafrica/archive/2014/09/01/a-day-of-devops-release-management-software-quality-and-agile-project-requirements-management-cape-town-and-johannesburg.aspx" target="_blank"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hope to see you there!&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  <ispublished>true</ispublished>
  <categories>
    <category>news</category>
  </categories>
  <comments></comments>
  <viewCount>26253</viewCount>
  <id>766de1fc-9caa-4086-aa6f-440f6b95c40f</id>
</post>