<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<post>
  <id>03668746-5f30-4079-93cf-00ba2ecc9847</id>
  <title>BITE–Branch Info Team Explorer Extension</title>
  <slug>bitebranch-info-team-explorer-extension</slug>
  <shortUrl>http://bit.ly/1iJ1auq</shortUrl>
  <author>Colin Dembovsky</author>
  <pubDate>2013-07-02 08:38:00</pubDate>
  <lastModified>2020-04-08 19:02:38</lastModified>
  <content>&lt;p&gt;Update 2013-08-30: The extension is now available for &lt;a href="http://visualstudiogallery.msdn.microsoft.com/85185516-dfe6-44e6-aa64-892cbff0e98a" target="_blank"&gt;VS 2013&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Branching is something that you should definitely be doing if you’re a modern developer. It doesn’t matter if you have branch-per-release or dev-main-live kind of branching – you need to be able to separate development streams.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So let’s pick on the classic dev-main-live scenario. You create a solution in Visual Studio (in a MAIN folder), check it into Source Control in TFS and then create branches to DEV and LIVE. Now you have three versions of the same solution – one on each branch. I always recommend opening from Source Control so that you know which branch you’re on. However, if you’ve opened the solution and then been working for a while, you may want to double-check which branch you’re working from. Hmmm, you’re stuck – there’s no way to do this other than checking the folder path for the solution.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Enter BITE&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Wouldn’t it be cool if you could instantly see which branch your solution is on? And how about selecting one of the other branches and clicking a “Switch” button to switch to the same solution on another branch? Now you can – using BITE – the Branch Info Team Explorer Extension! (Yes, I know it’s cheesy, but I couldn’t help it once I’d seen the acronym).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Once you’ve installed the extension from the &lt;a href="http://visualstudiogallery.msdn.microsoft.com/1d61464c-65af-4d25-af15-3b6b6919c56e" target="_blank"&gt;VS Gallery&lt;/a&gt;, you’ll see a new Link under the Pending Changes section:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://lh4.ggpht.com/-gvgJxO3NjxI/UdJ1VaPQlvI/AAAAAAAAA8g/Z1aLvetvQhU/s1600-h/image2.png"&gt;&lt;img title="image" style="border-left-width: 0px; border-right-width: 0px; background-image: none; border-bottom-width: 0px; float: none; padding-top: 0px; padding-left: 0px; margin-left: auto; display: block; padding-right: 0px; border-top-width: 0px; margin-right: auto" border="0" alt="image" src="http://lh6.ggpht.com/-cFPhFgEFITg/UdJ1WvjRyaI/AAAAAAAAA8o/cDryt8aM4vI/image_thumb.png?imgmax=800" width="203" height="244"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Click on “Branch Info” to see the extension in action.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://lh6.ggpht.com/-UeRKHCH7Lk4/UdJ1XMB_rUI/AAAAAAAAA8w/Si3T8G_ARZU/s1600-h/image9.png"&gt;&lt;img title="image" style="border-left-width: 0px; border-right-width: 0px; background-image: none; border-bottom-width: 0px; float: none; padding-top: 0px; padding-left: 0px; margin-left: auto; display: block; padding-right: 0px; border-top-width: 0px; margin-right: auto" border="0" alt="image" src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/-CpT7_b_rqPc/UdJ1YKi0eRI/AAAAAAAAA84/iCklL1PlQhs/image_thumb3.png?imgmax=800" width="283" height="206"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Here I’ve opened a solution on the MAIN branch (see the Current Branch label). I can see both the local and server paths for the solution. Also, there’s a drop-down labelled “Other Branches”. If I select one of the other branches, I can click the “Switch” button and the corresponding solution opens.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Let me know if you have any issues using this extension. (In case you missed the link, get the extension from the &lt;a href="http://visualstudiogallery.msdn.microsoft.com/1d61464c-65af-4d25-af15-3b6b6919c56e" target="_blank"&gt;VS Gallery&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Happy branching!&lt;/p&gt;  </content>
  <ispublished>true</ispublished>
  <categories>
    <category>development</category>
    <category>source control</category>
  </categories>
  <comments>
    <comment isAdmin="false" isApproved="true" id="e6fd5094-b71c-43a6-81d6-848b0dcfc485">
      <author>Anonymous</author>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <website></website>
      <ip></ip>
      <userAgent></userAgent>
      <date>2013-07-02 14:27:51</date>
      <content>This looks like a great extension!  However, it doesn't play very nice with a Dark theme!  very hard to read black text on dark grey background.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Thanks for the extension!</content>
    </comment>
    <comment isAdmin="false" isApproved="true" id="54e2d349-827e-4a28-872f-1f3c73df664f">
      <author>Colin Dembovsky</author>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <website>http://www.blogger.com/profile/02577890234096457646</website>
      <ip></ip>
      <userAgent></userAgent>
      <date>2013-07-02 15:49:50</date>
      <content>Oops! Guess who never uses the Dark Theme!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I've updated the extension to make it theme-aware - it plays much better with the Dark Theme now. Great catch!</content>
    </comment>
  </comments>
  <viewCount>7171</viewCount>
</post>