<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<post>
  <id>a8dea587-aec4-47ca-9315-be1c5e333c5d</id>
  <title>Pimp Your Consoles on Windows</title>
  <slug>pimp-your-consoles-on-windows</slug>
  <shortUrl>http://bit.ly/2zDDsOH</shortUrl>
  <author></author>
  <pubDate>2018-09-28 14:45:35</pubDate>
  <lastModified>2018-09-28 14:45:35</lastModified>
  <content>&lt;p&gt;I spend a fair amount of time in consoles - specifically PowerShell and Bash (Windows Subsystem for Linux) on my Windows 10 machine. I also work with Git - a lot. So having a cool console that is Git aware is a must. I always recommend &lt;a href="https://www.powershellgallery.com/packages/posh-git/0.7.1" target="_blank"&gt;Posh-Git&lt;/a&gt; (a PowerShell prompt that shows you which Git branch you're on as well as the branch status). At Ignite this I saw some zsh consoles in VS Code on Mac machines. So I wondered if I could get my consoles to look as cool. And it's not just about the looks - seeing your context in the console is a productivity booster!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It turns out that other than installing some updated fonts for both PowerShell and Bash, you can get pretty sweet consoles fairly easily.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Updating Fonts&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fonts that the custom shells use are UTF-8, so you'll need UTF-8 fonts installed. You'll also need so-called "powerline" fonts. Fortunately, there's a simple script you can run to install a whole bunch of cool fonts that will work nicely on your consoles.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here are the steps for installing the fonts. Open a PowerShell and enter the following commands:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre class="brush: powershell;"&gt;git clone https://github.com/powerline/fonts.git
.\install.ps1
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;This took about 5 minutes on my machine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;PowerShell&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;So to pimp out your PowerShell console, you'll need to install a couple modules: &lt;a href="https://www.powershellgallery.com/packages/posh-git/0.7.1" target="_blank"&gt;Posh-Git&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.powershellgallery.com/packages/oh-my-posh/2.0.225" target="_blank"&gt;Oh-My-Posh&lt;/a&gt;. Run &lt;font face="Courier New"&gt;Install-Module Posh-Git&lt;/font&gt; and &lt;font face="Courier New"&gt;Install-Module Oh-My-Posh&lt;font face="Calibri"&gt;. Once both modules are installed, you need to edit your &lt;font face="Courier New"&gt;$PROFILE&lt;/font&gt; (you can run &lt;font face="Courier New"&gt;code $PROFILE&lt;/font&gt; to quickly open your profile file in VSCode). Add the following lines:&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre class="brush: powershell;"&gt;Install-Module posh-git
Install-Module oh-my-posh
Set-Theme Paradox
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can of course choose different themes - run &lt;font face="Courier New"&gt;Get-Theme&lt;/font&gt; to get a list of themes. One last thing to do - set the background color of your PowerShell console to black (I like to make the opacity 90% too). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now if you cd to a git repo, you'll get a Powerline status. Sweet!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://colinsalmcorner.com/posts/files/a1a635c3-cc83-461d-a821-fcbb04a06ec0.png" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img width="699" height="308" title="image" style="margin-right: auto; margin-left: auto; float: none; display: block; background-image: none;" alt="image" src="https://colinsalmcorner.com/posts/files/f829659d-0185-4c9f-bfb0-8c663b615448.png" border="0"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Bash&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can do the same thing for your Bash console. I like to use &lt;a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell" target="_blank"&gt;fish shell&lt;/a&gt; so you'll have to install that first. Once you have fish installed, you can install &lt;a href="https://github.com/oh-my-fish/oh-my-fish" target="_blank"&gt;oh-my-fish&lt;/a&gt; - a visual package manager for fish (and yes, oh-my-posh is a PowerShell version of oh-my-fish). Once oh-my-fish is installed, use it to install themes. You can install agnoster by running &lt;font face="Courier New"&gt;omf install agnoster&lt;/font&gt; - I like bobthefish, so I just run &lt;font face="Courier New"&gt;omf install bobthefish&lt;/font&gt;. Now my bash console is pimped too!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://colinsalmcorner.com/posts/files/413ad7e5-a037-4fad-9691-41fb8798fef6.png" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img width="683" height="387" title="image" style="margin-right: auto; margin-left: auto; float: none; display: block; background-image: none;" alt="image" src="https://colinsalmcorner.com/posts/files/1b0ceee7-2ab0-4dfb-a12d-2ba8bcfcd985.png" border="0"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Solarized Theme&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;One more change you may want to make: update your console colors to the Solarized theme. To do that, follow the instructions from &lt;a href="https://github.com/neilpa/cmd-colors-solarized" target="_blank"&gt;this repo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you're going to work in a console frequently, you may as well work in a pretty one! Oh-My-Fish and Oh-My-Posh let you quickly and easily get great-looking consoles, and Posh-Git adds in Git context awareness. What's not to love?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Happy console-ing!&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  <ispublished>true</ispublished>
  <categories>
    <category>development</category>
  </categories>
  <comments></comments>
  <viewCount>0</viewCount>
</post>