<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<post>
  <id>d64076ea-5dd2-4256-83d1-2193124f9e60</id>
  <title>TechDays and Jhb Training Class</title>
  <slug>techdays-and-jhb-training-class</slug>
  <shortUrl>http://bit.ly/SjXl5b</shortUrl>
  <author>Colin Dembovsky</author>
  <pubDate>2012-10-01 17:14:00</pubDate>
  <lastModified>2020-04-03 19:48:50</lastModified>
  <content>&lt;p&gt;I will be co-presenting with Ahmed Salijee at &lt;a href="http://www.microsoft.com/southafrica/techdays/Home.aspx" target="_blank"&gt;TechDays&lt;/a&gt; in Durban, Johannesburg and Cape Town (12, 16 and 19 Oct respectively). Check out the website for details on exact dates and venues – there is tons of new stuff to show off, so this is going to be a really exciting event!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Here’s the blurb for the demo Ahmed and I will be doing:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;End to End Application Lifecycle Management with Visual Studio and Team Foundation Server 2012&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Microsoft’s application lifecycle management tooling is all about enabling teams to deliver great software. In this demo-packed session, learn how to engage early and often with your project’s stakeholders to ensure that your team is building the right software for them. Discover tooling to help you more effectively plan and track work by using the new web-based project management tools. Learn how to bridge the divide between development and operations by utilizing IntelliTrace in your production environments and integrating Microsoft System Center with Microsoft Visual Studio Team Foundation Server. And, developers can stay on-task and “in the zone” with the new “My Work” and code review features. In addition to making your team more productive, we show you how you can boost your overall code quality with new features such as code clone and an overhauled unit testing story in Visual Studio 2012. We will walk you through an end to end scenario from conception to production, leveraging capabilities across the define, build and operate phases. Feature covered include storyboarding, manual and automated testing, build, source control, code review, intellitrace and lab management.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Training Course&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;I am also going to be running a 2 day overview class in Johannesburg at Bytes in Midrand on 19/20 November. This course will quickly upgrade you from VS/TFS 2010 to VS/TFS 2012 so that you can get going quickly. The cost is R3500 per seat. You can get the course flyer &lt;a href="http://sdrv.ms/STrGoG" target="_blank"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hope to see you at TechDays or at the training course!&lt;/p&gt;  </content>
  <ispublished>true</ispublished>
  <categories>
    <category>news</category>
  </categories>
  <comments></comments>
  <viewCount>43813</viewCount>
</post>